Number 53.
53號
Got it.
好的，沒問題
-Do you need a bag? -Nope.
-要不要袋子？ -不需要
No chopsticks, no spoons. I'll use PayPay.
不要筷子，也不要湯匙 用PayPay支付
Shut up. Go home already!
吵死了，回家去！
How does Aimyon know how I feel?
愛繆怎麼會知道我的心情？
She doesn't!
她不曉得啦！
A breakup song sung
失戀的男人唱的失戀歌曲就像員工餐
I'm leaving.
我先走囉
What do you mean?
什麼意思？
When someone's singing at a karaoke, and they're not good or hilariously bad,
卡拉OK雖然唱得不怎麼樣 又沒爛到能夠嘲笑的地步
it's the most stressful thing.
其實讓人壓力最大
I'll end with "Dried Flower."
那我最後唱首《乾燥花》
Don't.
拜託不要
You're making me hate my favorite songs.
你會讓我越來越討厭原本喜歡的歌
I don't want to go back to that room.
我不想回那個房間
I can't forget the six days I spent with Kyoko.
我無法忘記和恭子一同度過的那六天
I won't forget how you kicked me out after we lived together for half a year.
你趕走了我這個半年來的室友 這件事我也不會忘的
So this is what loss feels like.
這就是失去的感覺啊
A world without Kyon Kyon…
沒有恭恭的世界…
Don't call her that after she dumped you, stupid.
別在被甩之後 才叫人家“恭恭”，笨蛋
Have you finished handing over your tasks?
交接結束了嗎？
Yeah.
是啊
I've found a good successor.
接班人選也順利決定了
I'm Kurita, the manager of Risk Management.
我是風險管理部部長，敝姓栗田
Thank you.
我收下了
Nice to meet you.
還請多多指教
You know, Mr. Ogawa,
真是不敢相信
I never dreamed you'd introduce me to Ms. Sakisaka.
小川先生居然會引薦向坂小姐
She's the complete opposite of me, but a good fit.
我和她是截然不同的兩類人 但她確實合適
She's more than welcome.
非常歡迎
We can highlight our corporate governance.
她的加入亦有助於我們 展現強化治理的方針
I'll also be diving into promoting gender equality.
我也會深入探究性別平等議題
True.
說得沒錯
Anyway,
總之我有在逐漸處理後事
Are you really okay?
這樣真的好嗎？
I've pretty much done all I could,
能做的我大多都做了
and I've got a rough idea of what my future holds.
大概也知道未來會如何
I even got to meet my grown grandchild and great-grandchild.
還見到了長大成人的孫女 甚至是曾孫
I had a lot of interesting experiences.
我在這裡體驗了好多趣事 這些經歷可珍貴了
For a future like this,
為了這美好的未來
your grandpa could give it a bit more effort.
外公似乎還能再加把勁
I wouldn't mind if you stayed forever.
你一直待著也沒關係啊
But I guess you can't.
但想也知道不行
Maybe I could,
我的事先不提，不過我得顧好純子啊
She'll have hanky-panky.
不然她會做那檔子事
I'm excited to see her.
我很期待見到她
She'll be thrilled.
她一定會很開心
But…
但是啊
don't act like her daughter.
你不是以女兒的身分見她喔
I know.
我明白
I'll act like an older sister just like I did last time.
我會像上次一樣 以年長姐姐的身分見她
Hey!
你們兩個！
You totally forgot about me, didn't you?
徹底忘了還有我這個人吧？
I did.
我是忘了
I wish you had already gone home.
還希望你能回家去
When a guy's just had his heart broken,
剛失戀的人
he's like the main character 24/7.
在未來24小時內都是主角
You can't forget about him or ignore him!
不能遺忘或無視啦！
How's your father?
你爸身體如何？
Ogawa!
小川！
Father!
爸！
Can I help?
-要我幫你拿其中一樣嗎？ -不用啦
I need some exercise.
我需要適量運動
Sorry for visiting.
抱歉
It's just I might not see you again.
我想說以後就見不到你了
So…
我們終於要說再見了嗎？爸
The time machine,
我想為小渚 進行最後一次的時光機之旅
You know,
因為啊
she's been rather down lately.
她最近沒什麼精神
-Here. -Oh.
-給你 -好
This won't be the last time we see each other.
我們也不是再也見不到了
Not at all.
會見到的
In fact, you'll see me again four years from now.
對爸來說，是未來四年後的事情
This is Yuzuru Inushima.
他是犬島讓
I'm going to marry this man.
我要跟他結婚
I hate to say this,
不好意思
but I doubt I can approve of your marriage.
我仍不會答應讓你們結婚
Right.
好的
Please don't.
爸就別答應吧
I can't marry her off to a guy with such wide shoulders.
我不能把女兒 交給肩膀寬得誇張的男人
Are you sure?
真的可以？
Nagisacchi won't be born.
那小渚就不會來到這世上了耶
Don't worry about that.
用不著擔心
I'm pregnant.
我懷孕了
You bastard!
你這混蛋
That means…
所以說要是我當下挺身反對 堅決拆散你們…
You bastard!
你這王八蛋！
It's fine.
沒問題的
It doesn't matter how much you oppose it.
不管爸再怎麼反對
My name might mean "yield," but I will never yield.
阿讓都不會讓步
I'm the champion of Roppongi, after all.
我可是六本木的霸主呢
Father, do you see?
爸，我的誠意就如你所見
Please believe me.
爸，相信我吧
Eventually, Nagisacchi will be born,
之後小渚降生於世
and Junko and I will pass away.
我和純子則撒手人寰
However,
然而在2024年
you will travel through time and appear before me.
爸會搭乘時光機，出現在我面前
Nice to meet you,
很高興認識你
sir.
伯父
A bunch of things happen.
然後發生許多事
I return to Showa, and four years later,
在我回到昭和的四年後
you will come to see me.
你會來見我
-And I won't approve. -Please don't.
-我不會允許你們倆結婚 -不用允許沒關係
You bastard!
你這王八蛋！
Nagisacchi will be born,
之後小渚誕生
Junko and I will die…
我和純子死後
And in 2024,
2024年
you will travel through time and appear before me.
爸會搭乘時光機出現
Nice to meet you,
很高興認識你
sir.
伯父
I return to Showa, and four years later…
-在我回到昭和的四年後… -來吧…
-Let's stop. I feel sick. -Right.
-別說了，我快吐了 -我同意
What should we do about this Falsetto?
該拿這個假音男怎麼辦？
It's even affecting his work.
也影響到了他的工作表現
He burst into tears at a client's place.
他會突然在客戶面前潸然淚下
I want to Kyon Kyon with hanky-panky!
我想做那檔子事，也想要恭恭啦！
Can't we do something to help him with your app?
不能用你們的應用程式想點辦法嗎？
The latest version features a lock-on hyper-matching mode,
最新版加入了鎖定屬性模式
which lets you lock onto a partner who shares a 99% compatibility.
可以鎖定契合度99%的對象
But only the users themselves can register for this system.
不過系統必須由本人登錄
Hey, you can't do that!
那種做法萬萬不可啊
How do I do it?
怎麼用啊？
Sorry, I dozed off.
抱歉，我睡著了
You should start getting ready soon.
你差不多該準備了
The bus leaves at 4:55 a.m.
4點55分得搭公車呢
The return bus departs in 11 hours at 3:55 p.m.
回程時間是11小時後的3點55分
Don't be late.
請勿遲到
It's a self-driving bus,
由於是自動駕駛，公車會按時出發
Right. We hear you.
好，我們知道了
Shall I go too?
要我一起去嗎？
Don't. You'll go "eeee" again.
不用啦
Isn't…
話說回來
the send-off team small?
沒幾個人來送行呢
Don't you think more people could've come?
再多找幾個人來嘛
Like Yashima.
比方說八嶋
He declined because it was too early.
他說“太早了，恕我拒絕”
I should've guessed.
他還真是失禮啊
Maybe I'm not popular enough.
看來我果然沒什麼人緣
I can call my dad.
要叫我老爸來嗎？
No need. I'll see him anyway.
不用，我們在另一個世界還能見面
And he's not that special to me.
而且我對他感情沒那麼深
Please send Kiyoshi back.
阿清的事就麻煩你了
Even if he hates it and you have to use force, put him on the bus.
不管他再怎麼不情願 也要逼他上公車
Right.
好
Please inform me
勞煩你轉告過去的我
that the Mutsugoro Kingdom will close down.
“彈塗魚先生的王國將會瓦解”
I promise…
我…
to find happiness.
一定會獲得幸福
It's all about yourselves, huh?
各位交代的都是自己的事耶
Mr. Ogawa, you too…
小川先生
It's okay to take better care of yourself.
你該更加重視自己
Just kidding.
我只是說說而已啦
Thanks.
謝謝你
To save fuel,
為了避免浪費燃料
my students will push the bus to the bus stop.
本校的學生會把車推到公車站
-Good morning!
-早安！
-What?!
啥？
-Hup, two!
-用力推…
Will this work?
還行嗎？
I'm super worried.
我超級不安的耶
Yes!
很好，引擎發動了！
Close the window!
關上車窗！
-Put more!
-用力推… -再來…
Good work!
辛苦了！
Thanks.
謝謝大家
Huh?
嗯？
SCHOOL-6-URA
（都營公車，六中裏 往工大正門前）
Welcome to Showa.
歡迎來到昭和
Well?
覺得怎麼樣？
It stinks.
好臭喔
Stinks? That's a first.
我還是頭一次聽人 說出“好臭”這種感想
Well, you'll get used to it.
算了，你遲早會習慣的
Nagisa!
渚小姐！
-Junko, how have you been? -Great.
純子，過得好嗎？
I'm coming in.
打擾了
Is that…
這位是…
Grandma?
外婆？
No, that's my mom.
不，她是我媽媽
He's my geezer's wife, but she's not an old woman.
雖然是我家老頭的太太 但也不算老太婆吧？
She passed away at 35, after all.
她35歲就過世了
-Where are you going? -Uh…
你要去哪？
Just going for a smoke.
我去抽根菸
You can do it here.
在室內抽不就好了？
Right.
也對
Nah.
還是算了
I'll smoke outside.
我去外頭抽
What was your mother like?
她是什麼樣的母親？
Yuri?
你說百合？
She was a bit quirky.
個性有些古怪
Ichiro.
-市郎先生… -是
What did you have for lunch today?
你今天中午吃了什麼？
Let's see.
我想想
I had my dear wife's bento box.
我吃了太太做的愛妻便當
Let's see.
我想一下
The breaded chicken breasts
炸雞胸肉
The omelet was sweet and delicious.
玉子燒帶點甜味，特別好吃
That's what fueled my victory today.
那道是致勝關鍵，沒錯
What do you think is for dinner?
你覺得晚餐的配菜會是什麼？
Let me think.
會是什麼咧？
I'm getting a strong whiff of curry.
咖哩的香味撲鼻而來
Lastly, what do you want to say to your wife?
最後請對妻子說句話
Yuri, I love you more than anything in the universe!
百合，在整個宇宙中 我最愛的就是你！
Love you too!
百合也愛你！
That happened every night?
每晚都上演？
Every single night.
對，每晚都會
Even as a kid,
雖然當時年紀小 但也覺得自家父母有點怪
What about your mom? What was she like?
渚小姐的媽媽呢？
Uh…
這個嘛…
The oldest memory I have of her…
我對她最早的記憶
was when I was around five.
大概是在五歲那年
My grandpa came from Tokyo to visit.
我外公從東京來訪…
Nagisa, your grandpa from Tokyo is here.
渚，外公從東京來囉
I could tell my dad was nervous.
我爸緊張得要命
Welcome.
歡迎光臨
Even though I was just a kid.
當時還年幼，但我還是看得出來
Come on, Nagisa.
來，渚
Sit on Grandpa's lap.
要不要讓外公抱？
I could kind of tell
我其實明白
it was up to me to ease the tension.
自己那時應該設法緩和尷尬的氣氛
But I wasn't sure how.
但我不知道怎麼做才好
And Grandpa smelled like cigarettes.
外公身上又一股菸味
I see.
是喔
Do you have a photo?
有沒有照片？
No.
沒有耶
But…
可是啊
I remember.
我還記得…
That awkward feeling…
當時的尷尬氛圍
and the smell of cigarette smoke.
還有菸味
Hey!
嗨！
You seem well.
你看起來很有精神
MAIYOMI NEWSPAPER
（《每讀新聞》）
You're back.
你回來啦
I came back to watch Tonight.
我太想看“TONIGHT”就回來了
What will you do?
你想怎麼做？
You couldn't have hanky-panky with Junko,
就算沒辦法跟純子做那檔子事
but you saw boobs on terrestrial TV.
你還是在無線電視台看到女生胸部啦
Aren't you craving
你差不多想喝星巴克的 芒果星冰樂了吧？
I am.
我想喝
Well,
那公車3點55分發車
So say bye to your friends.
去跟朋友道別吧
Here you go.
來
Please enjoy.
請慢用
-Let's dig in.
-我開動了
What is it?
幹嘛？
Are you
你是向坂清的…
Yeah, we're living together.
對，我跟他在同居
Where did Sakae go? I want to get in touch with her.
紗加惠小姐去哪了？
Um…
那個…
Did I do something wrong?
我做錯什麼了嗎？
I can't remember what it was.
我一點印象也沒有
Besides,
再說了，她那個人啊
Huh?
奇怪
Yasumori?
是安森嗎？
What's up?
你怎麼了？
Is she a hostess?
帶出場的酒店小姐？
Is this a paid date?
你們在店外約會？
Huh?
你說什麼？
Keep it in moderation.
出門在外記得收斂一點
Lemon squash.
給我一杯檸檬汽水
Right.
好
Bill, please.
麻煩結帳
Coming.
來了
Sorry.
抱歉
So much has happened in such a short span.
短時間內發生了太多事
-Shall we eat? -Yeah.
-我們吃吧 -好
I don't think your junior colleague is still angry with you.
我覺得你那位後輩應該沒在生氣了
I'm trying for a baby.
不好意思，我要備孕
I'm not sure.
那可不一定
Everyone can get wrapped up in their own stuff sometimes.
任誰都有只顧得上自己的時候
In those moments, people's words and attitudes
當下旁人的言辭或態度
can sting like glass shards.
會像玻璃碎片刺進心裡
Once she calms down and reflects,
但冷靜下來想想
I'm sure she'll see that you didn't mean it like that.
她一定會明白 渚說那番話不是為了傷害她
Oops, sorry.
我不小心叫你“渚”了
I didn't mean to be bossy.
抱歉，該叫你“渚小姐”吧
It's fine.
叫我“渚”就好了
Anyway, I think she is regretting it now.
所以我想啊 那個女生現在肯定很後悔
She probably wants to apologize, but it's just awkward for her.
我猜她只是拉不下臉認錯 其實心裡很想向你道歉
It's good.
真好吃
Goodness!
搞什麼嘛
You can cook well when you try, Barkeep!
原來你認真起來做的料理 這麼好吃啊，老闆！
Me?
你說我？
The Napolitan!
拿坡里義大利麵啊！
It tastes so different!
吃起來味道完全不一樣！
Why? Did you change something?
為什麼啦？
No, it's the same old.
沒有啊，是照老方法做的
You should always prepare it this way, then.
那你每次都要照老方法做啊
You're a pro, aren't you?
你可是專家耶
Don't make it soggy and mushy!
別做得又濕又軟爛
Nagisa.
渚小姐…
You've got ketchup on your face.
你沾到番茄醬了
Really? Where?
有嗎？哪裡？
Let's sit.
坐下吧
I'm changing schools.
我要轉學了
Oh, yeah?
是喔
When?
什麼時候？
Today.
今天
Huh.
這樣啊
I've lost even more motivation to go to school now.
那我更沒有理由去上學了
Well,
好啦，你吃過拿坡里義大利麵
What other Showa-era activity is there?
還有什麼是有昭和風格的？
The no-panties cafe got busted, after all.
不穿內褲的咖啡廳也被檢舉了
I've had enough.
我已經滿足了
I'm full.
而且吃飽了
I see.
這樣啊
-Hey. -I know!
大家好
Riding behind Mutchy on his bike is a Showa thing to do!
可以請阿睦學長騎機車載你 算是昭和特產吧
Akitsu?
秋津？
Yeah.
對
-I'm Mutsumi Akitsu. -Yeah.
-我是秋津睦實 -對
He's Akitsu's dad. Don't they look exactly alike?
秋津的老爸就是他 是不是一個模子刻出來的？
Wait, you changed your look.
等等，你的風格好像變了
You're giving off Senri Oe vibes.
很像大江千里呢
I bought these
是我買的
from the DC brand.
這可是DC品牌呢
Sorry, Mutchy!
抱歉，學長！
I was late because I got caught up drawing my eyebrows.
我畫個眉毛就遲到了
You look cute.
真可愛
SCHOOL-6-URA
（都營公車，六中裏 往工大正門前）
Thanks, everyone.
謝謝你們大家
I wasn't expecting such a crowd.
竟來了這麼多人送我
A larger send-off team isn't necessarily better.
送行的人多不一定是好事
Kiyoshi.
阿清
These past six months have been a blast.
這半年我過得很開心
Thanks.
謝謝你
Junko…
純子學姐
-Me too. -Sakisaka.
-我也… -向坂
Say hi to your mother. Don't forget.
代我向令堂問好 拜託你一定要轉告她
Write me.
記得寫信給我們
Call me.
記得打電話給我們喔
Yeah.
好
Huh?
嗯？
"I can't say goodbye."
“我無法說再見
"You idiot!"
笨蛋！”
Who are you?
誰啊？
Tell my future self,
替我轉告未來的我
the Mutsugoro Kingdom is everlasting!
-彈塗魚先生的王國永恆不滅！ -好
Here comes!
來了！
Thanks,
衷心感謝你
Mr. Ogawa.
小川先生
So I'll never see you again.
我們已經無法再見了
I'll see you again.
我是還能見到你啦
But you…
但是渚…
You wouldn't know me.
你不會知道我是誰
It didn't tingle.
沒有觸電般的感覺耶
Take care of yourself.
要保重喔
Take care.
你也是喔
Grandpa.
外公
Grandpa?
“外公”？
She meant I'm an old man.
她是想說我很老吧
Dad.
爸爸
Mom.
媽媽
Please
請你們友好相處
Hey.
喂
It's almost time.
快發車了
What about this?
手機怎麼辦？
Keep it.
你拿著吧
I'll get a new one.
我會請爸媽買新的
Thank you, Junko!
謝謝你，純子學姐！
Kiyoshi!
阿清！
Junko!
純子學姐！
Take care!
你要好好生活喔！
Thanks for showing me your boobs!
謝謝你讓我看胸部！
What?!
你說什麼？
Bye-bye!
再見囉！
Who are you?
你們是誰？
My predecessor, Ogawa, left this?
前職員的小川給你這個？
Yes, 30,000 yen.
對，有三萬圓
So, you two had a same-sex marriage?
兩位是同性婚姻關係對吧？
Yes,
沒錯
using the partnership system.
善用了伴侶制度
Takeda works for an IT-related company
竹田在資訊科技業的公司
and received a money gift.
拿到了結婚津貼
I got 30,000 yen.
共三萬圓
But EBS said they couldn't provide a gift unless we could prove our marriage.
然而EBS電視台表示 沒有結婚證明就不給付
A TV station is supposed to be progressive.
電視台可是走在時代的最前端
It should recognize same-sex marriage.
為何會不認同同性婚姻？
That's why we went to him.
我們找他商量這件事…
Hold up!
等一下！
Here. It's not much, but…
給你，雖然不多，請收下
No, that's not what we were asking for.
不用啦，我們沒有那個意思
Take it! It's the least I can do.
沒關係，只是我的一點心意
I can't accept this.
不行，我不能收
Just take it!
你收下吧…
So he was pretty accepting of same-sex marriage, huh?
原來他對同性婚姻挺寬容的
I'm not sure if he fully grasped it, though.
我是不清楚他是不是真的理解啦
Anyway, I'll return this to you.
總之這三萬圓還給你們
No, please don't.
不能還…
I don't need it.
我不需要…
It would be weird for me to take it.
我收下也不合理吧
And I'll help you get
而且我會提供協助
dependency allowances and other welfare benefits.
促成公司認可 扶養津貼等各項福利制度
It's what you deserve.
這是你們應享的權利
KATSUSHIKA WARD JUNIOR HIGH SCHOOL 6
（東京都葛飾區立 第六國中）
I'm sorry
我休了這麼久的假，真不好意思
You don't smoke, Ms. Takasugi,
高杉老師不抽菸 所以我買了環保袋給你
Did everyone get one?
大家都拿到了嗎？
-Thank you. -Thanks.
-謝謝
The only one left is the principal.
接著剩校長了
Mr. Ogawa!
小川選手！
Where have you been for the past six months?
這半年你去哪了啊？
Training.
我去進修啊
Didn't the principal inform you?
怪了，你沒聽校長提起嗎？
We should celebrate your return.
得辦個慶祝會歡迎你回歸
-Yasumori! -Yes?
-安森 -是
Time to bond over drinks!
一起喝幾杯促進感情吧
Let's do it.
好的
So noisy.
有夠吵
-Yasumori. -Yes?
安森
Where's the principal?
-是 -你有看到校長嗎？
Let's step outside.
我們出去聊聊吧
They made him quit?!
校長被辭退了？
Why? What did he do?
為什麼？他幹了什麼好事？
Actually, the principal…
其實校長他…
was a pervert.
是個變態
Streaking?
或是裸奔？
Could you please explain?
可以解釋一下嗎？
He was going as far as Shinjuku and Ikebukuro on his days off
他會選在假日特意前往新宿或池袋
to dress in drag and stroll around, which some parents noticed.
扮女裝在街上遊走 結果這一幕被家長目擊…
Hold on.
慢著
Is it a crime to dress in drag?
扮女裝是犯罪嗎？
Isn't it a crime?
不算嗎？
No, it's not.
不算啦
Groping is a crime,
猥褻是犯罪
but dressing in drag is just a hobby.
但扮成女生應該算個人愛好
Anyway, go on.
算了，你繼續說
This person is a surgeon,
這個人是外科醫生
and this one's a bureaucrat.
這個人是官員
Secretary.
這個人是秘書
People with similar interests dress up and meet up.
我們志同道合 會在梳妝打扮後聚在一起
Then, over lunch,
享用午餐
we chat about cool cosmetics
然後聊哪種化妝品好
or cute underwear being sold in Harajuku.
還分享原宿有在賣 可愛系內衣褲的消息
We swap information like that.
我們就是在互相分享那類情報
Stop, I don't want to hear it!
別說了，我們不想聽！
Aren't you embarrassed as a clergyman?
你是教職員 做這種事不覺得羞恥嗎？
I'm at a loss for how to apologize.
真不知該怎麼向各位謝罪
Why are you apologizing?
為何要謝罪？
Because it's setting a bad example!
因為這種行為會帶壞孩子！
Let's make this clear.
給我說清楚
Are you going to stop drag or quit teaching?
你要發誓之後不再扮女裝 還是放棄教職？
In that case, I quit.
-那我選擇辭職 -什麼？
LETTER OF RESIGNATION
（辭呈）
That's terrible.
太超過了
Absolutely.
就是啊
I never expected that from him.
沒料到他是那種人
No, I'm referring to you people.
我是指你們這些人啦！
It's just a personal hobby.
這是個人愛好
He's not bothering anyone, and yet you all bashed him.
沒給人添麻煩，你們卻卯起來責怪他
This is seriously messed up!
問題可大了！
Mr. Ogawa, you've…
小川老師，你好像…
changed somehow.
變了耶
No, I haven't.
我才沒有變
May I?
可以說句話嗎？
That guy came here last Saturday, right?
你說的那個人週六來過，對吧？
Keep it in moderation.
出門在外記得收斂一點
Lemon squash.
給我一杯檸檬汽水
Right.
好
Bill, please.
麻煩結帳
I saw him later that day.
後來我親眼目睹了
Thank you.
我要享用了
Goodness!
搞什麼嘛
You can cook well when you try, Barkeep!
原來你認真起來做的料理 這麼好吃啊，老闆！
Me?
你說我？
And I thought he looked like a pretty nice chick.
我覺得是個好女人
Are you serious?
真的假的？
So for the time being,
綜上所述，校長一職
Vice-Principal Saeki will be filling in for the principal.
暫時會由佐伯教務主任代理
I really can't stand Saeki.
我不喜歡佐伯那傢伙
He's so boorish
性情粗俗
and boring.
而且又無趣
Men's greetings and women's skirts
男人的問候語和女人的裙子一樣
should be short, after all!
都是越短越好
-Cheers!
-乾杯！
I want to go home.
好想回家
Is this really a welcome back party for me?
這真的是替我辦的歡迎會？
Excuse me, can you take our order?
不好意思，可以點餐了嗎？
With pleasure!
好，我很樂意喔！
He said "with pleasure," but he's taking his time.
說是這麼說，人卻不過來
Guess you can't expect much given the low wages.
就這麼點時薪，也沒辦法怪他啦
Ms. Takasugi.
高杉老師
Can I have a sip of that?
我可以喝你那杯一口嗎？
Here you go.
來
Where did you drink from?
我看看你是從哪邊喝的
Don't say that!
真是的，不要！
My predecessor just didn't have what it takes.
說穿了，是上一任校長太軟弱
And it turns out, he was gay.
而且還是男大姐
He brought shame upon the legacy of School 6.
抹黑了我們六中的傳統歷史
Dressing in drag doesn't necessarily mean someone is gay.
男大姐和扮女裝不能混為一談
And it's "men's speeches and women's skirts."
還有啊，正確來說是 “男人的致詞和女人的裙子”
Speeches and skirts alliterate.
“致詞”和“裙子”有押頭韻
Either way, it's inappropriate.
雖然問題不在這，發言依舊不妥
O-ga-wa!
小川！
Go easy on me!
拜託你高抬貴手
Yeah!
-來吧，地獄小川！ -地獄小川！
Youngster Yasumori, what's going on with the truant?
新人類安森 那位拒絕上學的學生怎麼樣了？
Do you mean Tsuyoshi Sako?
你是說佐高強嗎？
Well, it's not looking too good.
這個嘛，他比較棘手
Sometimes you need tough love.
愛的鞭笞有時是必須的
You need the harshness of lions pushing their cubs off a cliff.
獅子將子女推下懸崖的嚴厲行為
What's missing here is communication.
是源自於溝通不足
You've got to open up and have a chat,
交流時必須推心置腹
and value both vertical and horizontal connections--
-要重視縱向和橫向的聯繫… -聽了就倒胃口
Hey, Mr. Ogawa!
等等，小川老師
Why emulate lions?
為何要拿獅子舉例？
You're not Mutsugoro.
你是彈塗魚先生啊？
We're humans, both teachers and students.
老師和學生都是人
"Open up"? "Vertical and horizontal connections"?
推心置腹？縱向和橫向的聯繫？
At a mandatory drinking party?
在強制出席的餐會上說這什麼鬼話？
That's just peer pressure!
這不就是同儕壓力嗎？
Ogawa…
小川
Each student is
每個學生啊
different from the other.
都是獨一無二的個體
You can't simply impose the idea of willpower on them and call it a day.
套用從別處聽來的精神論 你確定這樣就完事了？
These kids are the ones who will shape the future 30 or 40 years from now.
那群孩子將打造30年、40年後的未來
Let's treat them with care!
我們要認真點！
H-Hey.
等等，小川老師是怎麼了？
Yeah.
就是說啊
Your sound arguments are tiresome.
老說大道理多沒意思啊
What?
什麼？
Come on, Ms. Oversized Tits.
來，大胸舞老師
Pour some more sake for the deputy principal.
給代理校長斟杯酒
Right.
好的
You don't have to do that!
你用不著幫人斟酒！
Regardless of being a woman or young, you don't have to settle for that role!
不要因為自己是年輕女性 就甘願接受這樣的事！
If people are being revolting, tell them so!
面對噁心的傢伙就直說“噁心”！
I'm…
我…
leaving!
要回去了！
-Mr. Ogawa! -Mr. Ogawa.
-小川老師！ -小川老師
Thank you for waiting. What's your order?
久等了，要點什麼呢？
Bring 200 plates of Broiled Shime Saba!
這桌上兩百盤炙燒醋漬鯖魚
With pleasure!
我很樂意！
You could've gotten that one!
剛才那球本該能接到！
Get lower in your stance!
腰再低一點！
What's going on? What?
幹嘛？怎麼了？
Please spank us with a bat.
勞煩老師揮棒擊臀！
This is stupid.
好蠢啊
Gather around!
集合！
Listen up.
都給我聽好
As of today, Ogawa from Hell is retiring.
地獄小川從今天起就要引退了
From now on…
從這一天起…
I'm Ogawa from Heaven.
我是佛祖小川
Those guys who become pros
能成為職業選手的人
take action before they get yelled at.
會在被罵前自動自發地行動
Keep that in mind.
給我銘記在心
In the future,
在未來日本將培育出 一大批大聯盟選手
who'll be global stars.
受全球矚目
A pitcher who wins a home run title.
像是投手兼全壘打王
A two-way player.
二刀流的選手
He's got a head this tiny.
臉蛋只有這麼小
And his butt is right at my face level.
屁股位置跟我的臉同高
How am I supposed to spank someone like him, huh?
我有什麼臉拿球棒打那種人的屁股？
Are big leaguers popular with girls?
加入大聯盟會受女生歡迎嗎？
What do you think?
那當然啊
What's the matter, Inoue?
井上，怎麼了？
I want to practice!
繼續訓練吧！
Right.
好
Let's practice.
練習吧
Make sure to stay hydrated.
記得不時補充水分
Wake up, ugly!
起床，醜女！
You female gorilla in heat!
你這個發情期的母猩猩！
-I'm already up. -Huh?
-我早就醒了 -什麼？
Didn't I tell you I've got a practice exam and a meeting with the teacher after that?
我說過啦，今天有模擬考
You've changed, Junko.
你變了呢，純子
Who is this guy?
這個人是誰？
Don't you know Abe?
你不知道阿部嗎？
He's the model for MEN'S NON-NO.
他是《MEN'S NON-NO》的阿部
Well,
對了
what about me?
你覺得我怎麼樣？
Have I changed?
有沒有變化？
Huh?
什麼啦？
What're you talking about, geezer?
說什麼傻話？老頭
-Cash, please. -Uh…
-給我錢 -哦
Here.
拿去
Here's your bento box.
你的便當
Huh?
什麼？
I might've made the omelet too sweet.
不過玉子燒可能甜了點
Good luck.
考試加油
Looks like it's just us again. At least it's cozy.
又要跟你這個老頭相依為命
If you say stuff like that, I'll remarry.
說那種話小心我再婚
Go ahead and try.
你儘管試試啊
You farting geezer.
臭屁老頭
No matter how hard she studies,
即使她在努力
I already know Junko's future.
但我知道純子的未來
Your daughter is amazing.
令嬡很厲害
She could enter college straight from high school.
她有能力應屆考上大學
Don't say that!
別那麼說嘛！老師
I'm serious.
我是說真的
Up until April, her grades were at the very bottom.
她四月前還是萬年墊底
Her standard score was just 30.
偏差值30
She was the lowest-scoring delinquent and look at her now!
排名倒數第一的不良少女 曾經是個墊底女老大
Junko doesn't have to go to college.
純子不上大學也沒關係
Get a job after high school.
高中畢業就上班吧
Work at a bar or even in sexual services.
從事特種行業或色情行業也行
What are you saying, geezer?
胡說什麼？老頭
Aren't you thrilled? I got an A.
你看了不高興嗎？我成績是A耶
You worked so hard, Ogawa!
你真的很努力呢，小川！
You used to be too dumb even for AGU's kindergarten.
你之前還笨到連青山學院大學 附屬幼稚園都進不去
It's okay for Junko to be dumb.
純子當個笨女孩就好了
I wish you'd stayed dumb!
若你還是個笨蛋那有多好
Do you think…
我還是應該…
I should tell Junko the truth?
對純子說出真相嗎？
Who cares about the time paradox?
誰管什麼時間悖論？
It's my duty as a parent to save my daughter.
救自己的女兒是身為父親的責任
But I can't tell her.
我說不出口
Nagisacchi won't exist.
說了小渚就不會出生了
More than anything,
更何況…
Junko seems
我們女兒現在看起來特別幸福
Maybe I've changed.
我變了嗎？
What do you think, Yuri?
你是怎麼想的？百合
Is it bad for me to change?
我不能改變嗎？
It's only natural, right?
自然會改變，對吧？
Especially after all I've learned.
畢竟懂了那麼多事
You probably got an update.
我看你是更新了吧
An update?
“更新”？
Learning about diverse perspectives
接觸多元化的價值觀
gave… update.
市…先生本人…更新了
No way.
這不是真的吧？
Yuri?
百合？
Where are you?
你在哪？
-Yuri? -Mr. Ogawa?
-百合？ -小川先生？
Calm down.
冷靜點
It's me,
是我啦
Sakae.
紗加惠
So it's you.
原來是你
What is it?
找我有事嗎？
You're the one who called.
是你打給我的
Mr. Ogawa,
老師
if you don't update your phone to the latest version,
你得將手機更新到最新版本
it'll stop connecting.
否則無法接通
How's it going there?
你們那邊還好嗎？
We're managing.
有在努力度日
Kiyoshi is buckling down on his studies.
阿清也開始做最後衝刺了
How's Nagisacchi?
小渚呢？
She's back at the office tomorrow, so I'll tag along just in case.
她明天就要復工了 我會陪同，以免出問題
I'm very sorry for causing you worry and trouble.
這次讓你擔心，也給你添麻煩了
Right.
嗯
If there's anything I can do…
若有什麼是我能做的…
Don't give her the obvious kid-glove treatment.
別說了，不要明顯 把她當成難搞的人對待
Welcome back, Nagisa.
歡迎回歸，小渚
I got out for some outdoor filming after so long. It was a blast.
有機會時隔許久去拍外景 我覺得挺開心的
Have you been following Mr. Yashima's bathhouse adventures?
八嶋先生出演的 公共澡堂巡遊節目你看了嗎？
I love how he dilutes the bath and gets scolded for it every time.
擅自加水降溫 結果每次都挨罵，這橋段太棒了
So hot!
好燙！
YASHIMAN'S BATHHOUSE ADVENTURES
（嶋哥的澡堂散步）
Here goes. It's hot!
我泡進去囉，好燙！
Hot!
燙死人了！
So the water is 42 degrees, right?
伯父，這水溫是42度吧？
It's so hot.
真的好燙
My bath is always at 39 degrees.
我家的洗澡水只有39度
What, 39 degrees? He's not a kid anymore.
39度？又不是小朋友
So hot!
好燙！
Oh! That's risky! Stop!
糟糕，有風險！暫停一下！
Isn't it showing?
有沒有走光？
-Um… -Huh?
-那個… -什麼？
Yashima Junior is showing!
這邊隱約看得見小八嶋！
Excuse me!
請問一下！
Sugiyama…
杉山是不是調走了？
Yeah, she works on the 20th floor in the annex,
對，她到分棟的20樓去了
in the contents management department at the new contents rights office.
所屬部門是新成立的 內容版權局內容管理部
It's fewer hours, so it shouldn't be too tough for her.
勤務工時短 我覺得她做起來還算輕鬆無壓力
That's a relief.
太好了
That was my biggest concern.
那是我最擔心的事情
I'm really glad.
-真的太好了 -叮囑你一句
you don't try to apologize in person.
請你千萬不要當面去跟她道歉
Is it that bad?
果然不行？
Of course, it is.
當然不行
For her, what happened with you is traumatic.
在她看來跟你之間的 那件事算是心理創傷
It might trigger flashbacks.
那樣做有可能讓她回想起當時的情境
Have you seen Hiromi Sugiyama's social media?
你看過杉山弘美的社群帳號嗎？
"My power-harassing superior is coming back to the office."
“聽說職權騷擾上司要復職了
"I want to puke."
好想吐”
That's horrible.
好過分
I'm appalled by your lack of sensitivity in sharing this with her.
有問題的是瓜生先生
No, this isn't locked, so anyone can see it.
等等，但她沒限制閱覽對象 誰都看得到
This…
那種行為遠比直接面對面更加暴力
This is verbal violence.
算是言語暴力
I hear you,
不好意思
but the company doesn't want any more victims or perpetrators.
站在公司的立場 不希望再出現更多受害者和加害者
I understand, but…
明白歸明白
Saying whatever you like on social media and blocking anyone you don't like.
想說的話發在社群媒體
This trend irritates me.
讓我心裡不舒服
Maybe staying in the Showa era has changed me.
我是不是在昭和待久了 所以也改變了？
Things here aren't much better, though.
昭和糟糕的程度也不惶多讓
The deputy principal took a bully to the victim's house
代理校長帶著霸凌加害者
and had them apologize in person.
到受害者家侵門踏戶 直言要對方道歉
Seriously? What kind of show is that?
啥？那算什麼作秀行為？
Not only that, he gave a passionate speech at a PTA meeting.
最終還在家長會前熱情演講
The bullied must share some of the blame as well.
我想被欺凌者之所以受人欺凌 也是有原因的
Please talk about it at home.
請各位家長和孩子好好談談
That's terrible.
糟透了！
Living in the Showa era is tough.
昭和這時代無法活得自在啊
I want to go back to Reiwa!
我好想回令和
I want a salad sushi roll from Sushiro while watching LOVE It!
我想邊看“Love It！” 邊吃壽司郎的沙拉軍艦壽司
Well, let me share a few cases I had to deal with today.
既然如此 要聊聊我今天處理的案子嗎？
"We got a complaint about the lack of women in the Sentai series."
“戰隊裡唯有粉色代表女生一事
"They claimed it's a remnant of patriarchy."
受到了抗議 稱此為父權制的遺留問題
"Should we also include homosexuals?"
但同志戀人也該納入其中嗎？”
What?!
什麼？
"Should we copy streaming sites and avoid showing men's nipples?"
“男性是否該自我約束 避免於直播中露出乳頭？”
Are you kidding?
那算什麼？
"I'm being accused of harassment by an assistant director,
“被助理導播控告職權騷擾
but it's completely unfounded."
被告稱作騷擾的事卻沒發生過
"When I said it was harassment harassment,
主張此番指控為抹黑騷擾
they claimed that was harassment."
結果原告說此舉即是騷擾
"In other words, harassment harassment harassment."
換句話說，就是三重職權騷擾
"Now I'm facing countercharges."
對方反而如此控告”
No!
不！我搞不懂令和！
What's wrong? Are you okay?
怎麼了？沒事吧？
-Sorry, could you hold this for me? -Sure.
-不好意思，幫我拿這個 -好
Maybe there's a rat.
不曉得是不是老鼠
I keep hearing a rattling noise in the toilet.
廁所裡一直在砰砰響
Can we agree both Showa and Reiwa are tough to live in?
結論就是昭和跟令和都不好生存
They're both tough to live in.
兩個時代都不好生存
And neither are tolerant.
而且不夠寬容
Totally!
沒錯！
Tolerance isn't the same as indifference.
寬容和粗枝大葉是不同的
The kid-glove treatment isn't it either.
把人當作麻煩精看待也是錯的
I hate informal events and drinking parties.
靠著講真心話或灌酒 來交流感情的飯局最難搞了
No matter what someone did to you,
無論遭受何種對待
to say "I want to puke" about another person isn't right.
“想吐”這種話都不該對別人說吧？
Totally!
說得沒錯！
We're not smartphones.
我們畢竟不是智慧型手機
We're humans.
而是活生生的人
So even if one person couldn't get an update,
即便某一方沒有完成更新
as long as the other is tolerant, we can still get along!
另一方寬容一點就還是能和睦共處
Tolerance!
問題就出在寬容！
We need more tolerance!
世人不夠寬容！
I have been nagging
雖然至今
And complaining
講了那麼多
But at the end of the day
歸根結柢
Both the old and the young
無論是長輩還是年輕人
We should be more tolerant!
都再寬容一點吧！
There is no such thing as perfect equality
世上沒有完全的平等
Reiwa and Showa, men and women
令和與昭和，男人和女人
Differences in looks, personality, taxes
容貌、性格、納稅額皆不同
If they're slight differences
如果只是些微的差異
Let's put up with them
那就稍微忍一忍
Let's be forbearing
放寬心胸吧
Let's be accepting
沉著應對吧
I'm not you
畢竟我不是你
So I can't understand you 100%
無法100%理解你
If there's a 2% or 3% difference
對於合不來的2%到3%
Let's hold back
不禁會想在網上發言
From making comments
但忍住那股衝動
Let's be tolerant
讓自己寬容待人
Let's be forbearing
放寬心胸吧
Let's turn the power off
關掉電源吧
No matter what you say, you get bashed
說什麼都會引發輿論撻伐！
Bashed!
引起爭議！
Because that's how the world is
正因為世道如此
More than poison
比起毒舌
Tolerance is important
寬容更重要
Important!
重大而緊要！
Woman, you're so competent
你這傢伙真是個好女人
Woman?
“你這傢伙”？
Wake me up at six tomorrow
明天早上六點叫我起床
Don't wake me until nine
九點以後再叫醒我
I'm not your alarm clock
我又不是你們的鬧鐘
Let's be tol--
寬容…
No!
不對！
Tolerance isn't indulgence!
寬容和縱容是兩回事！
Saying woulda coulda shoulda won't help
說些假設也不會有幫助
Just stay focused on the future
只要向前看就沒問題
Look behind you every once in a while
偶爾也要回頭看看後方
Yield the way when you need to
該退讓時則退讓
And
然後呢
Let's be tolerant
讓自己寬容待人
Let's be Forbearing
放寬心胸吧
Is seventeen an adult?
17歲算大人？還是小孩？
We get all dizzy with risky romances
危險的戀情令人暈頭轉向
Only drink alcohol after you hit 20
滿20歲才能飲酒
In the next life, I
來生我會將你、你會將我
Will give you a hug from behind
自身後擁抱
So lame!
超級老土！
If they're slight differences
什麼？
Let's put up with them
那就稍微忍一忍
Diverse perspectives
面對多元化的價值觀
Embrace them
用寬闊的心胸
With an open heart
學著去接納
Let's be forbearing
放寬心胸吧
More than winning
比起不服輸
Tolerance is important
寬容更重要
Love still wins
雖然敵不過愛
But tolerance is also important
寬容也同樣重要
It won't fill your stomach
即使填不飽肚子
But tolerance is important
寬容依然重要
Let's be forbearing
放寬心胸吧
Hey.
我問你喔
Your company's matching app…
你們公司的交友應用程式…
You mean Un-MAY?
你說“命運”嗎？
It's useless.
這根本不準嘛
Huh?
什麼？
Why?
怎麼說？
It keeps suggesting you.
它老是推薦你
COMPATIBILITY 99.9%
（契合度，99.9%）
And it's really annoying how you're backlit.
這張逆光照真的讓我滿肚子火
Sorry about that.
真不好意思
Try turning off location services.
-你關閉定位功能試試看吧 -什麼？
I mean, my app keeps suggesting you too.
因為它也常常向我推薦你
What? No way.
不會吧？討厭
COMPATIBILITY 99.9%
（契合度，99.9%）
This photo is way too edited.
這張照片修圖修過頭了啦
Shut up.
閉嘴啦
I mean, how come our compatibility is showing as 99.9%?
話說我們的契合度為何是99.9%？
Huh?
奇怪
My preferences have been changed.
條件被修改了
"Works at a TV station."
“任職於電視台
"Divorced."
離過一次婚
"Single mom."
單親媽媽
"Loves comedy."
喜歡搞笑類
"In her early thirties."
年齡為30歲到35歲
"Within a kilometer radius."
住處距離一公里以內”
"An app development salesperson."
“從事應用程式開發、業務工作
"Recently heartbroken."
最近剛失戀
"Has an overweight father."
爸爸發福
"Enjoys cooking."
興趣是做菜
"In his late twenties to early thirties."
年齡是26歲到35歲
"Within a kilometer radius."
住處距離一公里以內”
You did this.
是你改的吧？
No, it must have been you.
不是我，是你改的才對吧？
How could I have done this?
怎麼可能
I didn't know your father was overweight.
我又不知道你爸發福的事
Can it be?
難不成…
Sorry, I dozed off.
抱歉，我睡著了
It was Mr. Ogawa.
原來是小川先生
It's got to be.
就是他啦
He's the only one who'd pull something like this.
也就只有他會做這種事
-Seriously. -Goodness.
-受不了他 -真是的
So,
所以呢？
what do you think?
怎麼辦？
What do you think?
你想怎麼做？
Should we try dating?
要不要試著交往看看？
Are you sure?
跟我嗎？
Yeah.
對
If Mr. Ogawa's behind this,
小川先生都這麼做了
it's worth a shot.
就試一試吧
I guess Mr. Ogawa is more trustworthy than an app.
小川先生比應用程式更值得信賴
I just feel like having someone close to me right now.
我現在很希望有人能待在我身邊
Still…
等等…
If you say no, I'll sing "Dried Flower."
被拒絕我就唱《乾燥花》
Please don't.
拜託不要
You sing "Dried Flower" when you get dumped. It's how it is.
告白、被甩然後唱《乾燥花》 是一套完整的流程
But…
可是…
think about it.
仔細想想
Didn't your dad and my mom…
你父親和我母親
have a thing going on at one point?
不是差點就交往了嗎？
And here we are, their children.
而我們分別是他們的兒子跟女兒
Our compatibility…
我們的契合度
can't be that bad, right?
應該還不賴啦
Just in case,
保險起見
scan this QR code.
還是掃一下QR碼吧
It's for a sexual consent app.
是性同意應用程式的
I guess you never know…
畢竟我們也不知道
what might happen.
兩人間會發生什麼事嘛
ASK YOUR PARTNER TO SCAN THIS QR CODE
（請對象掃描QR碼）
Do you want to come over?
要不要來我家？
-Happy New Year.
-新年快樂
-Good luck.
-先別走
-Good morning. -Happy New Year.
-早安 -新年快樂
-Hey, Yasumori.
-嗨，安森
Let's have a good year.
今年也請多關照啦
Congrats on becoming vice-principal.
恭喜你榮升教務主任
It's nothing to celebrate.
沒什麼值得慶祝的
I only got the position because he became the principal.
還不是那傢伙成了校長後替補上任
You can't complain if someone gropes you.
穿這麼短 要是被人騷擾也無法抱怨喔！
PRIVATE TUTORING
（WAM一對一教學）
RESULT: C
（本屆志願大學成績 考上的可能性為C）
Kiyoshi!
阿清！
You're Kiyoshi Sakisaka!
你是向坂清吧？
Student number 19. The Mysterious Transfer Student.
學號19的神祕轉學生
No way.
不會吧
Are you Sako?
佐高同學？
Yeah, I'm number 20. Tsuyoshi Sako.
對，我是20號的佐高強
I've been wanting to see you!
我一直想見你一面！
Me too.
我也是
You haven't changed one bit, Kiyoshi.
你都沒變呢，阿清
It's crazy how much you haven't changed.
就算沒怎麼變也該有個限度吧
But Sako…
佐高同學…
you've changed.
你倒是變了
I've been searching for you for so long.
我一直在找你
I wanted to thank you.
因為我想對你道謝
You should go to school.
你就去上學吧
School…
學校這種地方啊
is where you learn
會讓我們學到
there are people in this world you just can't get along with.
這世上也有和自己合不來的人
You spend three years there
我們會花三年的時間
confirming that everyone except you are crazy.
確認在學校除了自己以外的人 其實都不太正常
But if you manage to find
但如果能在此期間
one or two friends there,
交到一、兩個朋友就行
then you'll never have to see the others for the rest of your life.
其餘的人到死都不用再相見
I'm glad I met you, Sako.
我很慶幸能夠與你相識，佐高同學
And it's all because I went to school.
我得感謝學校
You get to connect with people you click with,
能跟志同道合的人來往
and avoid the ones you don't.
不必跟無法融洽相處的人交際
Lots of convenient things like that will pop up
把它當成方便的場所
Sako showed up.
佐高來了
-It's Sako! -No way.
-那是佐高！ -不會吧
-Shh! -Where?
-小聲點！ -哪個是他？
Act normal.
保持平常心對待他
-Act normal. -I know.
-保持平常心 -我知道
Happy New Year.
新年快樂
You were right, Kiyoshi.
你說得沒錯，阿清
After failing once, I entered high school.
我在考試落榜後，升上高中
And I started an online gaming company with a friend I made there.
和當時的朋友一起成立線上遊戲公司
I connected with programmers from all over the world.
與世界各地的程式設計師互相交流
And now I'm a CEO.
如今擔任執行長
My!
我的天啊！
What can I say?
我驚訝到說不出話了
I'm so impressed.
你出人頭地了啊
That's why I've been wanting to repay the favor.
所以我總想著有一天要報答恩情
I'll do anything to help you out.
只要能幫上阿清，要我做什麼都可以
Can you do something for Inoue instead of me?
不一定要幫我，幫井上可以嗎？
-Inoue? -Masakazu Inoue.
-井上？ -井上昌和
The one with a buzz cut and glasses.
還記得他嗎？就是那個光頭眼鏡男
He studies time machines.
他是時光機的研究員
He's looking for a sponsor.
他正在找贊助商
That's funny.
太有趣了吧
Listen.
聽好了
You're the only one I can turn to, Inoue.
我只有你能依靠啊，井上
Entering Sophia
進上智大學 加入青山學院大學的社團
Or entering AGU and hanging out at Sophia clubs.
或是去青山學院大學 加入上智大學的社團
Which would be more fun?
選哪種比較有意思？
Let's get accepted first.
要不要等考上再想？
At this rate, she will get accepted.
再這樣下去她一定會考上
she'll get married in college, have a daughter,
然後還沒畢業就結婚
Junko and I will become estranged.
我和純子會就此斷絕關係，所以你啊
As someone from the future,
請你以未來人的身分
you must warn everyone in Japan that a major earthquake is imminent.
警告全日本將會發生大地震吧
Hey, are you listening?
我說啊，你有在聽嗎？
I'll give up on the time machine.
時光機就算了吧
"Give up"?
什麼算了吧？
I want to become a big leaguer.
比起時光機，我更想進大聯盟
Hold on, Inoue.
等等，井上
You don't have a talent for--
你在棒球上的天賦…
They're popular, right?
那樣我就會有異性緣吧？
To marry a female announcer, that would be the easiest way.
想跟女主播結婚的話 打棒球應該是最短的捷徑
Hang on a second.
先緩緩
You saw a bus disappear the other day, didn't you?
你前陣子看到了吧？
What did you make of that?
親眼目睹公車消失 當下你有什麼想法？
-It made me realize that… -Uh-huh.
“時光機這種東西
the time machine already exists.
原來已經存在於世上了啊” 我只有這麼想
No, you're wrong!
不對…
You're the inventor!
你會做出時光機！
You invented it!
是你做出來的啦！
You're being noisy!
你很吵耶！
Fine.
好啦
I'll do it.
我做就是了
Forget baseball!
你沒有棒球天分啦！
SCHOOL 6 GRADUATION CEREMONY
（昭和61年度畢業典禮 葛飾區立第六國中）
TO THE FUTURE
（邁向未來）
-Cheers!
-乾杯！
Quiet, please!
大家安靜！
The vice-principal has something to say.
教務主任要說幾句話
Hey!
大家好！
Congratulations on your graduation.
恭喜各位畢業
I feel sorry for you,
生在這種時代
being born in this age.
你們真可憐
The smell of cigarettes is everywhere.
到哪裡都菸味瀰漫
You get spanked for things someone else did.
受連帶責任牽連，被打屁股
And finally, you're graduating.
終於熬到畢業
But don't worry.
不過放心吧
Your future is going to be interesting!
你們的未來將會很有意思！
Inappropriate and violent teachers like me will be a thing of the past.
不會再有我這種極度不妥的暴力教師
If you use a sleek gadget to order an Uber,
用一種光滑的物品叫優步外送
you can enjoy a Big Mac right at home.
在家就能吃大麥克
But even in that future age, adults will tell kids,
不過在那樣的時代 依然會有大人對小孩說
"I feel sorry for you for being born in this age."
“生在這種時代真可憐”
You don't have to listen to adults like that!
但那種大人說的話大可不必聽！
Instead, today, I have a special surprise for you.
我今天不多說什麼，要給你們聽聽
I'll let you listen to music from the far, far future.
來自遙遠未來的音樂
Go ahead!
麻煩你們了！
Who are they?
他們是誰啊？
-What's that? -What's going on?
-那是什麼？ -好酷
You're trending again.
又上熱門了
"Seeing Mr. Yashima naked is perfect for a Saturday afternoon."
“八嶋先生的裸體 正適合週六下午看”
Really?
真的嗎？
Maybe you can book a Green Car seat for my next--
那從下次起讓我搭新幹線的 綠色頭等車廂吧…
Nagisa, listen.
小渚，聽我說
The drama starting tomorrow,
明天開拍的電視劇
the actor playing the protagonist's father got COVID…
本是主角父親的演員 得了新冠肺炎，我在緊急找人替代
I can fill in for him.
要我來代演嗎？
Excuse me.
不好意思
It's been a while.
好久不見
Yeah.
是啊
You seem well.
看來你過得還不錯
You too.
前輩也是
I got a boyfriend.
我交到男朋友了
I got a boyfriend too.
我也交到了
I see.
這樣啊
Are you trying for a baby?
備孕還順利嗎？
I stopped.
我放棄了
He wants it to be just us for now. He said kids can wait.
男友說還想過二人世界
I see.
是喔
I'm happy for you.
恭喜你
You too.
也恭喜前輩
Let's be tolerant
讓自己寬容待人
You're late!
太晚了吧！
Couldn't you have texted at least?
你啊，至少能跟我說一聲吧？
Yeah, my bad.
是啊，抱歉喔
Okay!
好！
It's Daddy!
是爸爸喔！
Here we go!
來抱抱！
Let's go to Daddy, Machato.
阿正讓爸爸抱一下吧
Sorry, he's pooping.
抱歉，他拉便便了
Change his diapers later.
你待會幫他換個尿布
Seriously, you really don't have a knack for parenting.
真是的，你真的很不適合帶孩子耶
It's me, Matchy!
我是阿真喔！
Excuse me. I'm Masahiko Akitsu.
不好意思，我是秋津真彥
Listen.
聽好了
You're free to date whomever you like, but…
雖然要跟哪個男人交往是你的自由…
Well then, be a good daddy.
我走了，那就麻煩爸爸囉
Bye!
再見！
Shouldn't you hear him out?
就這麼離開好嗎？他好像有話想說耶
It's fine.
不用管他啦
-What do you feel like eating? -Um?
想吃什麼？
Let me think.
吃什麼好呢？
Hey!
喂！
Wake up, ugly! It's the entrance ceremony today!
給我起床，醜女！
I know that! Shut up!
我知道啦！吵死了！
Geezer.
老頭
Cash, please.
給我錢
For crying out loud.
真拿她沒轍
She was only good until her entrance exam.
就只有升學考試期間安分守己
And university sure isn't cheap.
而且上大學要花真多錢啊
Even if I work hard to cover her tuition,
我上班賺錢付學費
she's just going to have hanky-panky with some guy.
她卻會跟來歷不明的男人做那檔子事
Are you listening, Barkeep?
老闆，你有在聽嗎？
A rat?
是老鼠嗎？
KYOKO KOIZUMI "KOGARASHI NI DAKARETE"
（小泉今日子 《寒風中的擁抱》）
Mr. Ogawa!
老師！
Sorry?
什麼？
It's me, Inoue.
我是井上
Your student, Masakazu Inoue.
你的學生井上昌和
I finally made it!
總算打通了
I finally got to see you!
終於見到你了！
You're Inoue?
井上？
You're old, though.
老爺爺就是那個井上？
Yes.
對
I've come from 2054.
我來自2054年
I discovered the time tunnel.
我發現了時空隧道
Thanks to Sako sponsoring me,
多虧有佐高同學出資
I was able to do lots of research.
我不斷地研究再研究
Unlike the bus, you can go to any era you like.
現在不須靠搭公車 我們可以隨意前往想去的時代
That hole…
難道那些洞也是你挖的？
Come, let's go to any era you want!
來，我們一起前往想去的時代吧！
No way.
不好吧…
This production features inappropriate dialogue.
（本作包含極度不妥的台詞）
Subtitle translation by: Ai Matsuoka
字幕翻譯：劉維容